Guide to the Hugo Leander Blomquist papers, 1912-2000, bulk 1917-1964. UA.29.02.0137
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hugo Leander Blomquist papers
1912-2000, bulk 1917-1964.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Blomquist, Hugo Leander, 1888-1964
UA.29.02.0137
2093
6.0 Linear Feet
Hugo Leander Blomquist was professor and chair of the Botany Department at Duke University from 1921-1957. The collection includes correspondence between H.L. Blomquist and his wife Margaret during the 1920s and during H.L. Blomquist's service in the Army during World War I, class notes, North Carolina maps, as well as drawings and photographs of his book The Grasses of North Carolina. The collection ranges in date from 1912-2000.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
Provenance
The Hugo Leander Blomquist papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1977-1978; 2007.
Biographical/Historical note
Hugo Leander Blomquist was born in Sorsele, Sweden in 1888 and moved with his parents to Kulm, North Dakota in 1892. He grew up on the family farm and attended public schools in North Dakota before attending the University of Chicago, where he received his B.S. in 1916. He took two years off in the middle of his undergraduate career to serve as principal of a high school in Deering, ND. From 1917 to 1919 he served as musician first class in the U.S. Army overseas; after the war, he stayed in Paris to study biological chemistry at the Pasteur Institute. When he returned to the U.S., he enrolled in the graduate program in botany at the University of Chicago, and earned his Ph.D. in 1921.
Blomquist joined the faculty at Trinity College in 1921 in the Department of Biology, specializing in fungi, algae, vascular plants and bacteriology. In 1935, when the Biology Department split into divisions of zoology and botany, Blomquist became Chair of the Botany Department. H.L. Blomquist married Margaret Mordecai in 1928 and the couple had one daughter, Betty. H.L. Blomquist retired from the Botany Department in 1957 and died in 1964; Margaret Mordecai Blomquist died in 1982.
Among Blomquist's publications include A Guide to the Spring and Early Summer Flora of the Piedmont, North Carolina, Flowers of the South, Native and Exotic, The Grasses of North Carolina, Hepaticae of North Carolina, Ferns of North Carolina and Vascular Anatomy of Angiopteris Evecta.
Scope and Contents note
Collection contains personal and professional correspondence of Hugo L. Blomquist from the years 1912 to 1961. Correspondence includes letters to his brother during Blomquist's service in the Army during World War I as well as correspondence between H.L. Blomquist and his wife Margaret Mordecai Blomquist before and after their marriage. Also includes materials related to Blomquist's time in the Army, citizenship process, maps, notes, and oversize illustrations and photographs associated with the publication of his book Grasses of North Carolina. Illustrations were removed from acidic paper wrapping and boxed for preservation.
Related Material
Dept. of Botany Records
Duke University Archives
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
Photograph Collection, 1861-2006
Duke University Archives
Kramer (Paul J.) Papers, 1856-1994 (bulk 1927-1974)
Duke University Archives
Oosting (Henry J.) Papers, 1937-1968
Duke University Archives
Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University. Department of Botany; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Faculty; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History -- 20th century
- Accessions A77-220, A78-145, 653869
  - Correspondence, 1927-1948, 653885 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1950, 653884 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 653883 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952, 653882 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1953, 653881 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1961, undated, 653880 (Box 1)
  - Blomquist/UNC Press Correspondence, 1952 January-1954 January, 653879 (Box 2)
  - Notes and Outlines, 653878 (Box 2)
  - Identification of Grasses by Their Vegetative Characters, Notes and Outlines, 653877 (Box 2)
  - NC Maps (1 of 5), 653876 (Box 2)
  - NC Maps (2 of 5), 653875 (Box 2)
  - NC Maps (3 of 5), 653874 (Box 2)
  - NC Maps (4 of 5), 653873 (Box 2)
  - NC Maps (5 of 5), 653872 (Box 2)
  - The Grasses of North Carolina, 653871 (Box 2)
  - Illustrations and Photographs for Blomquist's The Grasses of North Carolina, 653870 (Box 3)
- Accession UA2007-0041, 1912-2000; 2
  Scope and Contents
  Addition contains materials related to H.L. Blomquist's service in the Army during World War I as well as correspondence between Blomquist and Margaret L. Mordecai (his future wife) dating from 1924-1928. World War I correspondence includes Blomquist's letters to his brother during his service before and after deployment overseas, and letters he received from two women he met in France during the war. The addition also includes postcards, materials related to Blomquist's gaining United States citizenship in 1950, personal items (passport, smallpox vaccination certificate, honorable discharge), photographs, and journals from his WWI days containing his daily activitives and thoughts containing headings such as: "Impressions of Paris," and "Who won the war?" Materials range in date from 1912-1957. An addition of 0.5 linear feet was added to this accession 15 October 2007. The addition contains primarily letters and clippings. Also present are some photographs and a book of letters presented to Blomquist upon his retirement.
  - School programs and materials, 1912, 1916, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Identification and legal materials, 1917-1950 (Box 4)
  - WWI letters about Army experience prior to overseas deployment, 1917-1918; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Diary from France, 1918 (Box 4)
  - WWI overseas letters, 1918-1919; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Postcards, 1919, undated (Box 4)
  - French correspondence, 1919, undated (Box 4)
  - Materials during Army service, 1919 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (general), 1917-1932 (Box 4)
  - Notebook, 1921 (Box 4)
  - Notebook, 1921 (Box 4)
  - Notebook: Botany 7, undated (Box 4)
  - Letters to H.L. Blomquist from Margaret Mordecai, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Letters to H.L. Blomquist from Margaret Mordecai, 1925; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Letters to H.L. Blomquist from Margaret Mordecai, 1926; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Letters to H.L. Blomquist from Margaret Mordecai, 1928; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Letters to Margaret Mordecai from H.L. Blomquist, 1926 (Box 5)
  - Letters to Margaret Mordecai from H.L. Blomquist, 1927; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Letters to Margaret Mordecai from H.L. Blomquist, 1928; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (general), 1940-1964 (Box 5)
  - Letters to Margaret from H.L. Blomquist, 1946-1949 (Box 5)
  - Citizen materials, 1948-1950 (Box 5)
  - Letters to Margaret from H.L. Blomquist, 1953-1954 (Box 5)
  - Margaret Mordecai Blomquist Correspondence, 1940-1976 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook given to H.L. Blomquist upon retirement from Department of Botany, June 1957 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence regarding publications, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - Photographs, circa 1917-1960s (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1919-1964, undated (Box 5)
  - Notes and reprint, 1951, undated (Box 5)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 5)
  - Biography, Flora newsletter, photograph, 1970-2000 (Box 5)